[Music]
thank you
hello everybody
oh everybody is well
I need to mute
one second
can you hear me I suppose you can't hear
me now hey everybody uh great to be back
on the ask of this show I am reporting
live from the venue of the G20 Summit
here in New Delhi and it's uh it's great
to be back on the ask of the show it's
been such a long time I've been
traveling I've been busy doing things so
here I am
foreign
nightshirt gaming and excited science
user are kind of mapping is
H Raju nikhil
I
Kumar basically
Vladimir
Singh Rajesh
um hello
this is where the show is happening and
in case you are interested in seeing
what this place looks like I have a few
angles that I could offer to you
let's see what angles I can offer
uh take a look at this
I have multiple angles today
it's been a long day and I'm just having
some fun so let's see
if I can
let's see how how good the Wi-Fi holds
the laptop that I have has a good
internet connection let me see if I can
take you all around
and show you what this place looks like
uh let me
one second
maybe I can bring this over here
okay let's see let's see if I can show
you the please all right
so this is what the place looks like
here we are
I hope the image isn't Frozen or
anything
this is the place it's a huge huge place
there are still people over here working
as you can see
so this is the thing it's it's a huge
complex and the entire International
media
is over here there are lots of places
where people can but media people can
sit and work excellent internet
connections uh reasonably good Wi-Fi as
well
and as you can see it's enormous
so just a quick uh
at the place and now let me get back to
the laptop
and Michelle continue from there I will
take your questions for the next minimum
one hour maybe a couple of hours and
let's see so let's get back to oh my
what
station
okay
uh
yeah
okay this should do it all right now
let's take some questions
all right
Mike doubling okay let me just turn off
the thing from my phone so that way
it'll be fine
okay
all right so what okay did the practice
very kindly very graciously by the
government of India to come and cover
this uh extremely important
Summit the G20 Summit this is India's
G20 this is ABS presidency of the G20
and India has done a fantastic job of
organizing the whole thing the entire
event
not just this Summit but overall the
entire all the activities that happened
over the past year in more than 60
cities in the country uh more than 130
events if I'm not mistaken and millions
of people took part in some in some form
or the other
so yeah it was it's it's been a
brilliant draw by the government of
India so many people have participated
and uh
okay it looks like they are still
two mics on
okay
can we can you all hear me now properly
or do we still have a Cause
I hope we don't have any more Echoes
sometimes this is what what happens when
you
uh yeah
is it all good now I'll just check the
live chat and see all right everyone
think it's clear now out outstanding
good
so
um yeah so I was invited by the
government of India I'm very thankful
very grateful to the government for
adding me here a wonderful place and uh
that's why I'm doing this from here
today to give you a clipse of how uh
things are over here so I've been
inverted as a as a media person I'm not
really a journalist I'm a geopolitical
Observer and analyst but yeah I mean it
makes sense for someone like me also to
be here apart from
uh shall we call what should I say
the Legacy Media some of which you may
see behind me if you recognize faces
anyhow uh yeah that's what let's see
some other questions
Miguel the answer says what what
happened to miss you Mr to her Olaf
Schultz's eyes I I think he wears one
eye patch an eye patch or when I I think
he had some kind of accident while
jogging or cycling I think I was jogging
the bicycle bicycle accident was Mr Mr
Biden right uh so I think so Olaf
Schultz was jogging and maybe he fell
down or something there are some bruises
on one side of his face and maybe uh his
eye may have been injured or the area
outside so until it heals is gonna wear
the eye patch just uh yeah why not look
cool it's nice materials
I mean the his appearance right now
um
Esh says your take on the Bharat name
change well it's not official the
government hasn't made anything that uh
we're gonna change the name from India
okay uh what's happened is that in
there have been certain government
Communications in which the prime
minister of India has been referred to
Mr Modi the prime minister of Bharat
okay in the official uh what do we call
it communication printed communication
the Prime Minister similarly uh Madam
president has been referred to in
writing as the president of Bharat and
today during the G20 Summit when all the
uh world leaders were there in front of
the Prime Minister it said Bharat not
India
so it's not really a name change the
constitution of India refers to India
that is battle
so we already have two official names
right we have two official names and uh
many foreign countries also uh refer to
India and Bharat at the same time so
when I was a kid when I I spent a few
years in Switzerland and over there I
had this uh this poster of all the flags
of all the countries in the world and
you had the names of the Nations beneath
each flag and for India it said India
and into brackets Bharat so that was
like 30 years ago or I don't know 40
years ago 35 whatever right so even at
that time their referred to India as in
Arab at the time India's population was
about 600 million less than half of what
it is today uh so that's how it was so I
don't think we are official the
government is officially changing the
name and uh rejecting the name India I
think both names are going to uh be
equally valid there's been no statement
no communication from the government
that we are going ahead with the main
change if you do a name change it's
going to be a logical headache at least
you're gonna have to if you remove the
name India and insist on only
then you're gonna have to change every
passport every other card you're gonna
have to change all the official
documentation wherever it off whatever
kind it is you're gonna have to change
your currency notes in in coins and
whatnot and you're gonna have to make
some changes at the United Nations level
and other levels I think it's it could
be a logistical headache for sure I mean
it cost some money we do have the money
to do that but do we really want to do
that there the name India does have some
brand value so I think we can use both
names the government can use both names
so it's choosing to use one right now so
that's perfectly fine that's perfectly
legitimate there's nothing
unconstitutional wrong about it
officially change the name but in
official Communications we're gonna use
but officially it will still be known by
two names and there are lots of
countries like this for example China
the official name in Chinese is wrong
but everyone outside China calls it
China Greece we call it Greece but its
actual name is Hellas Japan the actual
name of Japan and Japanese is
right and what about Germany Deutschland
Germania
it has so many names like professor says
so uh many nations are known by the more
than one name and especially when it
comes to a nation like India that's so
ancient like thousands and thousands of
years old and and it's so large and so
uh
uh so it's been so influential it's
gonna have multiple names and various
Nations
referred to us by various names so
that's fine
so uh I don't think there's any name
change but it's interesting to see that
certain sections of Indian Society
uh and in the political class and and
the academic class perhaps they have
been very upset about any possibility of
a of a name change in a potential name
change and they've been uh coming out
very vociferously against it and that
tells you that there's a certain
attitude that these people have
um these are the the old OCR regime the
old Elites the ones who benefited from
the nehruvian era a very small group of
people a small group of people who have
had all the power and all the Privileges
it would be The Gatekeepers of
information in Academia and media and
everything and these are the ones who
you know who see it as India and not as
Bharat I think everybody else is not
south east west everybody thinks of a
Nation as Bharat more than as India and
Bharat is a civilization term India is
is the term that's been uh used by
foreigners and it's it's well the roots
go back to the persons and the Greeks
Persia is older than Greece and the
portions they
essentially migrants from India who went
and settled in what's now Persia now
called Iran uh and or and the language
changed so old portion the old portion
language was a derivative of a bunch of
language and the pronunciations were
kind of wonky you know uh so instead of
so they would say huh and therefore the
Great Rivers
and eventually the tricks came over here
and they mangled the name Hindu became
this or whatever
became the Indus
became the caucus
and eventually the so-called Western
Civilization
it considers Greece
Mesopotamia and Egypt to be its
Fountainhead
and that's why they have taken these
pronunciations that the Greeks have
imposed about the world and mangaed them
further and that's how the term India
was used by the British so the term
India is after if you look at all the
history that I just mentioned it's
overall a British term but it has its
roots in the portion of the Greeks
and so these people who are opposing the
name to each are the ones who love the
English way of doing things
and losing themselves as the
as the uh
uh the ones who carry forth the Legacy
for British colonialists
and they're the ones with the most
opposite so I have absolutely no no
issue with the Prime Minister and the
government of India and the president
referring to this great civilization as
Bharat instead of India I think it will
be good thing I call it Bharat in my
live streams in my videos because I have
a I would I have a large International
audience and I want to be intelligent
intelligible to them but yes in my heart
it's Bharat I mean every every true
Indian every two bharatiya will consider
the nation to be Bharat more than India
so yeah all that that's my opinion I
don't think the name is being officially
changed I would be very surprised if it
is but who knows yeah Prime Minister
Modi is is fond of getting surprises so
let's see and good surprises yep all
right let's see
uh Amit says love your podcast thank you
so much so thank you so much
dinner will be live on TV I'm not sure
no I don't think it's live I mean if it
were live I would see you know you know
there but I just show you a while ago
let's see if I can add this
so
and I should remove that angle otherwise
it's gonna have a doubles
double echoing sound once again
okay let's see what else do we have
saurabh says does the absence of
Vladimir Putin matter well look uh
when you have an email you would like to
have all the world leaders to be present
the ones who are part of the cheat with
deviations
um unfortunately Mr Putin could not end
and Mr Putin actually called up Mr Modi
a couple of weeks before today and he
informed him that he will not be able to
attempt
Summit that happened recently in South
Africa and we know
what compulsions Mr Putin is bound by
there is this raging War right now the
Ukraine war and uh Russia and the West
are at loggerheads and uh other Western
leaders if if Mr Putin were to come to
India for the summit it's very possible
that the West leaders like Mr Biden
Mr Mr Schultz and Mr sunak Etc they
would have perhaps refused to speak with
him Coach ordered them do you remember
how Prince uh Muhammad bin Salman was
treated in the in the
2018-19 G20 Summits he was treated like
a pariah like an outsider no one spoke
with him only prime minister spoke with
him and the same thing possibly would
have happened to Mr Putin only Mr Modi
would have spoken with him and given him
a worldly welcome everybody else would
have important who wants to
put themselves in that sort of a
situation and there's the added
complication of the international
warrant that's been put out for Mr
Putin's arrest which is ridiculous but
whatever so because of these matters and
to save Mr moti the host some
embarrassment because of the treatment
that could be meted out by the other
leaders that's the reason why Mr Putin
most likely did not attend and he called
up Mr Modi and explained his decision
his his decision not to come to the
summit to him so that was a very uh nice
thing to do he informed Mr Modi
personally in advance when it comes to
Mrs in a whole different story so it
would have been nice to have Mr Putin
here is one of the major world leaders
very powerful world and one of the most
powerful people in the world one of the
most influential and consequential
leaders in the world but unfortunately
he could not come because of all these
reasons so um
has the absence mattered uh it kind of
would have been good to have it but
overall he sent his representative the
foreign minister Mr lavrov I miss lava
was a very competent uh foreign minister
very good foreign minister and uh the
the event proceeded just uh as it should
otherwise have so
the absence wasn't felt that much
obviously the personality wasn't there
Mr Putin is someone that the media likes
to follow and take a look at and also
that was missing
so that's overall what Mr Putin
okay Paula Swami says what's your take
on the new middle east Europe Corridor
where's the map
we gotta have a map
so palash has given me the opportunity
to crack out the map and let's do that
so let's understand what this Middle
East Corridor is uh here we have Google
Maps
ah is visible now
So What on earth
why am I okay let's remove that let's
remove all this so what's this Corridor
middle India middle east Europe Corridor
that's what it is so it's going to be a
a trade corridor it's gonna involve a
real real link as well as shipping links
so it's going to start let's say from
India and India has multiple ports on
the western coast of India right so
let's say from any point in India I'm
gonna have a shipping link to the United
Arab Emirates and to Saudi Arabia
so it starts from India India is one of
the points or starting points which we
want to look at it and we're going to
have uh linkages shipping linkages with
the UAE and Saudi Arabia then it goes
forth into Europe
and uh it's gonna involve Italy it's
gonna involve Germany it's gonna involve
France and it's going to involve the
European Union overall so at some point
you're gonna have a rail route and from
India to the Arabian Peninsula you're
gonna have shipping routes and this
middle India middle east Europe trade
Corridor is also going to have uh an
electrical line it's going to have a
high speed data link hence with the high
speed data line and a hydrogen pipeline
as well so it's a multiplicity of things
and overall it's gonna make trade
between India and Europe faster it's
also gonna make the cost of trans
shipments cheaper maybe even 30 40
perhaps and the speed will also increase
by 30 40 percent
and overall it's it's gonna link India
to these nations more closely and the
bigger perspective here is that and also
it's not just these nations that are
involved in this it's also the United
States that's going to be involved
because as if you have been following
the things I've been saying uh the real
power in Western Europe is either
Germany nor France it's the United
States so the US is also involved in
this and uh Mr Biden has given its
blessing and the U.S is going to be
involved as well in this so what this
does
is that is going to and in India also
has the international north south
transport Corridor which involves uh
shipping links with Iran and then then
you will have a road in railings all the
way into into Europe where Russia and
other places
so this is kind of something that's
happening in parallel with that now this
new scheme the India middle east Europe
if you see it from a bigger larger
geopolitical perspective
it's arrival to China's dying built-in
Road
dri one belt one road
one belt to rule them on all one road to
bind them that sort of thing remember
so this is a rival to the Chinese belt
and Road initiative Bri and their
Maritime Silk Road or whatever and that
is more or less dead in the water
because nobody wants to be part of it
and the interesting piece of news Italy
Italy has withdrawn from the Bri in
Italy is going to be part of the India
middle east Europe Corridor big blow for
China
she obviously is here right now
somewhere here nearby
um yeah so that's a deal so it's very
important
this is a very important uh new project
and yeah so that's the thing right so
all the nations are coming together
and nobody wants to deal with China
nobody likes China I mean the
this expansionist imperialist hegemonic
power I know there are going to be
comments over here we're gonna say that
I'm very into China Hey listen we didn't
start anything with China it's a Chinese
who have always been the aggressors not
just with India but with all their
neighbors so I think the world has seen
through what China has been doing and
what China is up to and what China
really wishes and wants and desires and
dreams
right uh
and yeah so so we're gonna see more and
more of these initiatives that are going
to bypass the built-in Road initiative
and see in the case of the Bri it's all
run by China the Chinese make it a point
to say that this is our infrastructure
project
other nations are involved but we are
funding we are financing it and we are
constructing it
in the case of this new India Middle
East you know Corridor all the nations
that participate in it are going to be
more or less equals there'll be some
inequalities obviously some nations of
way uh larger and uh have larger
economies like India but overall all the
nations are going to be stakeholders and
no one nation is going to say that this
is our project
so it's a more uh inclusive egalitarian
thing and it's going to benefit a
genuine development all these nations so
very important new initiative that's
been uh that's just been uh you know
unveiled and and I can't wait for it to
become a reality
so overall very important and a great
development
all right what else let me see there are
lots and lots of questions uh I'm gonna
deal mainly with the G20 and and
politics in this session I can see
questions about other things as well
okay kushal says why is India not
properly commenting on Taiwan why can't
we invite Taiwan as a guest to indicate
when we look how does that benefit us
sorry China
Taiwan look Taiwan isn't that big of a
deal uh economically the G20 is overall
trade and economy grouping of Nations
they create an economic groups it's all
about trade and economy and the economy
it's not about uh some Alliance a
military Alliance or a geopolitical
Alliance there are nations within the
G20 that don't really see eye to eye I'm
in Russia and China don't see eye to eye
with the West India is the only relation
that gets equally well with Russia as
well as with the west and China nobody
essentially gets along with it even the
Russians don't trust China the Chinese
recently product map in which they have
reopened the ocean to be border Clash
disputed territory issue and they've
claimed Russian territory once again as
part of their own the Chinese nobody can
trust them so please I'm sure there are
commenters are saying right now that I
am anti-china listen the China rnt world
the Chinese are anti-world
um
so that's the deal so since the G20 is
uh
trade and economic uh full economy
focused uh grouping of Nations we don't
want to get geopolitical and you know
openly commenting on Taiwan listen I I
keep saying this maybe people don't
maybe it doesn't sink in
words don't matter actions matter
so I think India should
instead of augmenting about Taiwan and
starting a war of words very hard
criticism all that do something I'm sure
we're doing some things we're doing a
few things I mean recently a certain
Indian ministers did interact with
Taiwanese politicians and leaders and
I'm sure we have trade a trade
relationship going on that's how you do
things you don't talk about it you don't
start a war of words you don't show use
muscular language which is pointless you
actually do things on the ground so
that's the thing and what's the point of
inviting Taiwan as a guest what are they
going to gain from it
we have enough issues as it is with
China and uh yeah so there's no point
doing that from my perspective
all right what else do we have
what else do we have too many questions
yes lots of questions
um okay let's see this
the daily declaration got accepted by
all the countries how big of a victory
is this for India it's a huge victory
listen
last year uh for the Bali Summit there
was an issue of whether all nations
would be able to agree on a jointed
declaration and the Russians were
adamant that we will not allow any
inclusion of the term Ukraine in the
final joint declaration G20 declaration
body declaration and the Chinese were
also against uh using the term Ukraine
eventually some kind of consensus was
reached and prime minister modi's words
that this is not a time for war were
used those was used in the body
declaration this year it had been I
think uh it's a 37-page document I have
it open somewhere here I'm not going to
open and put it over here it's a 37-page
document who was the time to read it I
do but most of you want and want to do
that I'm sure so it's a 37 page document
uh more than 83 82 or 83 points lots of
paragraphs and the word Ukraine is
mentioned four types okay it's mentioned
four times and once again the same
the same language is used
which Prime Minister Modi had said to Mr
Buddha that this is not the time for war
and somehow I mean this was
expected to be a major stumbling point
it was expected that Russia would
essentially block any usage of the word
Ukraine or any reference to the war in
Ukraine in this declaration and it was
expected that the Chinese would support
the Russians in this and some I'm not
I'm not sure how it happened how it was
done but India got all nations including
China and Russia
to agree to the wording the language
that has been included in this joint
declaration the word Ukraine is
mentioned four times
and there's also a significant portion
on
on terrorism which essentially is China
throwing Pakistan under the bus because
the the one nation whose major export is
Terrorism is India's temporary
neighbor Pakistan right so it's a huge
victory for India I actually expected
that this would be a major fumbling
point and I was
I was thinking if it doesn't happen even
then it's gonna be a big victory for
India because India has held this Summit
very well and conducted the entire G20
uh presidency really well
so I was observing that even if the
joint declaration doesn't happen it's
still a huge success for India but this
is like it's it's exceeded expectations
it's really exceeded expectations and uh
India somehow got every nation all
countries including China and Russia to
accept this joint declaration it's a
huge victory for India it
okay sorry about that there are some
people who like to talk really loud for
no reason
and you don't need to anyhow uh so it's
a huge victory for India it's a huge
diplomatic victory for India it shows
India's leadership
it shows India's diplomatic prowess of
of getting everybody on board Nations
that are really
not open to doing sort of things I mean
Mr income he said his number two Oreo Mr
King kin or whatever his name is the
premiere
and he was Mr Olympics represented over
here and Mr lavrov was Mr
misrepresentative and we got everybody
along and got them to agree I think it's
a major major victory and this is
after the fact that this declaration got
accepted which contains so many of
India's initiatives it's it's going to
be it's going to go down in history as
the most successful G20 Summit date till
the year 2023 the first G20 Summit was
held in the year 1999 if my memory
serves me right and it was held in
Berlin
and uh so this is
most likely the 24th Summit that's
happened and this is going to go on
industry as the most successful Summit
until today so it's a huge victory for
India and uh I would congratulate Prime
Minister Modi and uh
and everybody else who has been involved
in this huge Victory magnificent
performance very well done I mean what
else can you ask for right all right all
right
let's see what else we have oh oh I saw
something yeah here we are XP gamer says
what do you think about the African
Union's addition to the G20 well you
know it's it's high time
you know one of the criticisms that G20
has faced is that it's it's a grouping
of the Rich and Powerful right that's
one of the major criticisms of the G20
has faced and this criticism
um has some truth behind it I mean the
largest continent in the world is Africa
and you're totally sidelining this
enormous continent and every nation in
it so it's it's they talk about
inclusivity and equality and all that
but you know they don't practice what
they preach so India has this has been
India's initiative that we need to bring
the African Union in and give it the
same status as the European Union in the
G20 so it's now essentially the g21 and
this is India's doing so some some
commentators will say that India Russia
China all push for this no no no no no
no no
it's India it's Prime Minister Modi and
it's India who insisted that the G20
must include the African Union and we
made this today morning it was
it was officially announced that the
African Union is now a member of the G20
and Prime Minister Modi um invited the
current leader of the African Indian to
join the other G20 leaders at the table
so it's a feta complete it's done I
think it's a great thing so now the G20
would g21 probably account for more than
85 percent maybe more than 90 of the
entire world's GDP with the inclusion of
the African Union I think it's a very
good thing it's great for
you know for for the for the betterment
of the world it's it's great from the
perspective of inclusivity of taking
Humanity forward
um so yeah I I think it's great and it's
gonna make India lots of friends it's
going to create a lot of Goodwill for
India in Africa so it's not just about
so there's there's that that angle as
well that perspective as well that is
going to win India lots of rights and
for good reason with good reason because
India made this happen nobody else was
willing to make this happen the Chinese
these days are portrayed themselves as
some kind of leader of the global South
well it is the Chinese that have been
exploiting Africa for resources
because the Chinese verb in spring in
dead traps on extremely poor African
nations this is Chinese that have been
propping up dictators it's the same with
the West does in Africa
but now that they are no longer on track
to becoming
a superpower now they want to certainly
become the leader of the global song
well it's not going to happen
it's India that's that's made this
happen it's on China that's made it
happen so overall I think it's a very
good development and I would like to
once again congratulate India the
government of India and the Prime
Minister Modi for making this happen and
you're gonna give credit where credit is
due you know who made this happen it's
the government of India it's Prime
Minister Modi who made this happen it
isn't somebody else who made this happen
understand that so I am giving credit
where credit is actually due
all right
what else do we have
um
what else what else what else what else
uh let me see some interesting uh okay
mihir says why
does Uzbekistan and its other X USSR
neighbors why are these nations not part
of the G20 well see
the original it's not the g21 the
original G20 was essentially a group of
the top 20 economies
that's essentially what it was and for
some reason they included the EU which
is not a nation but well when you when
you when you decide what the rules are
you can make any rules you can do
whatever you want with it so India then
took a leak out of the same Playbook and
got the African Union inserted into the
G20 wonderful great great job now why is
not part of the G20 it's a tiny
economies that's primarily the reason
why they're not part of the G20 they're
tiny Economist the very small economies
uh Kazakhstan
I think Kazakhstan is a very large
country
Uzbekistan I think Pakistan is the
largest one let's consult the map we
have the map why don't we do that one
second give me a second
okay let's take a look at the map yes I
was completely correct my geography is
good still good Kazakhstan is the
largest of these uh Central Asian
Republics
but unfortunately even though it's so
large its population is very small
relatively speaking and the economy
isn't anything uh very large either so
it's primarily because of the small size
of these nations economies that they are
not part of the G20 the G20 was
essentially a grouping of the top 20
largest economies and that's the reason
why it's not there well eventually you
can bring every nation into them then
but then it will become a new United
Nations so you're gonna serve you will
have a certain objective or gender and
all that so that's the reason why it's
not there
ah this is a good question Abhishek says
how come China agreed on this joint
Declaration of the g20d leaders what
changed their stance I think
there is nothing in the language of the
Declaration that is specifically and
explicitly
anti-russia or anti-china and there is
there are four mentions of Ukraine in
the Declaration but it none of the
none of the paragraphs none of the
language none of the none of the words
actually point a direct finger at either
Russia or China so the language has been
crafted in such a way that you do
mention Ukraine but you don't point an
accusatory finger at anyone you don't
blame anybody for starting this or that
or whatever so there's been this very
very intricate tightrope walk Walking
act a balancing act and India clearly
has done this masterfully and that's why
the Chinese had no choice but to agree
to the Declaration uh I am still a
little bit surprised the Chinese were
able to uh we were able to get the
Chinese on board because they have had
this very uh obtuse
uh attitude from the beginning of
India's presidents they've been
objecting to all kinds of things they've
been very Petty very vindictive very
cynical
they even objected to the motto of
vasudeva I'm saying that they Justified
their opposition to this by saying that
Sanskrit is not one of the languages
that's part of the G20 official
languages something like that
extremely Petty you know just annoying
Behavior well that's China for you so I
don't know how India got made this
happen but a full I mean kudos
to Dr Jai Shankar and to Prime Minister
Modi for even getting the Chinese on
board so great great success great the
success like what you would say
um
what else
could CSS from Pakistan Modi awesome
thank you sir thank you
um
what else
are you tired of this whole day after
this whole day it's been a long day it's
been a long day I am kind of tired but
hey you come here you walk you come here
you do what you're supposed to do so I
really wanted to give you guys a glimpse
of how things are and do a live stream
from here I'm not sure if anyone else
has taken the initiative of doing a
proper q a live stream from this place
there will be lots of live telecasts
half an hour one hour whatever the
various uh Legacy Media Outlets the
various News television outfits and all
but yeah I'm gonna do this live stream
and I'll show you a glimpse of how
things are over here I think I showed
you the whole thing once roughly and
yeah so yeah I'm a little bit tired but
hey I have way more energy left in
reserve so I'm good
okay what else do we have
uh Ahmad Jyoti biswold says did the West
raise Russia in water the summit I'm
sure they must have tried to raise it
and there is some reference to Ukraine
like I said in the in the joint
declaration the final declaration but
overall India was able to smooth things
over
and get things get everybody to come
together so um if you if you have seen
the uh telecast
of the various
sessions of the summit the first of the
summit there was no mention of Ukraine
I'm sure there must have been mentions
of Ukraine and discussions over Ukraine
during the Diplomatic negotiations that
went into the drafting that were part of
the drafting of the joint declaration it
has I'm sure it came out it came up but
India was able to get this done so great
all right what else
um
saurabh says why is Bharat not in the G7
well you know it's interesting that the
past the past few G7 Summits India has
always been invited in those summits
uh I can think of at least the last two
summons in which Prime Minister Modi was
you know was was one of the invites a
special in Mighty right uh so officially
India is not part of the G7 well you
know India should be part of the G5 or
G3 actually because India is already the
fifth largest economy in the world in
2014 India I think was the ninth largest
economy in the world so in nine years we
have reached to number five and by 25 26
in the next two three years we're gonna
surpass uh Germany and Japan we're gonna
be number three
so it makes sense for for them to invite
India whenever the G7 Summit is held
even though India is not officially a
member of the G7 because India is now
way too important to be ignored right
um
so I think
it used to be the G8 earlier and Russia
was a part of this but then after I
think it was after the Crimea operation
2014 they removed Russia from it
uh so maybe they can make it the G8
again and into India in it anyway invite
the Indian Prime Minister every year for
the G7 Summit so maybe they should
reconfigure the G7 making a G8 again and
have India as part of it because India
is too important now to not be invited
to any of these major uh summits
all right
what else
what souvenir did the organizers give to
people who attended the summit I haven't
received any souvenir I believe there's
some package that everybody was given
but I somehow seem to have missed it but
that's okay I didn't come here to get a
package or something I came here with a
purpose a specific purpose and I'm
carrying it out
um
and was I given something I
yeah I was going to badge
that's going to be my souvenir so yeah
that's all nothing else but yeah I mean
nothing to complain about I'm very happy
incredibly good uh
facilities over here there's nothing
that anybody from the media or would
have to complain about it's all
very well done very well done so so
kudos to the organizers very well done I
mean this is the way to to hold a summit
of this uh magnitude and consequence
very well done
okay
um how am I feeling there I'm feeling
great I'm feeling great
it's good fun
and overall it's it's good good to be
part of this so I'm feeling great
ah good question good question what do
you think about India's role in the
Saudi
Arabia's MBS and uh Biden and Sheikh
that's an interesting question let's
let's try and
try and
uh bring that one second
I think that I I have an image of that
so give me a second let me put that on
the screen
take a look at this
here we are so this is the uh handshake
that sebby Carls is referring to so this
happened just a couple of hours or less
than a couple of hours ago that Mohammed
bin Salman and Joe Biden shook hands and
Mr Modi uh was the third person in the
hand trick he actually brought those two
together and this is kind of significant
considering the fact that Joe Biden and
his administration have really targeted
Muhammad
over the Jamal khashoggi and Syrian and
other stuff as well and yeah it's not
been a good relationship ever since Joe
Biden came to power
and even before that Americans have
really gone after Muhammad bin Salman
they have targeted him for being a
human's right human rights abuser and
and whatnot the standard Playbook
and as as a consequence the whole new
geopolitical uh scenario has opened up
in the Middle East with the Saudis
trying to distance themselves from the
Americans and and trying and trying to
you know open up new possibilities new
avenues new geopolitical alliances new
energy alliances from themselves and
divest themselves of the millstone that
is the U.S Alliance
so considering all that it's kind of a
significant event that Joe Biden and
Mohammed bin Salman shook hands at the
insistence or with the with the uh
facilitation of Prime Minister Modi and
Mr Modi the third person to hold their
hands so I think it's good so it it
demonstrates the entire world knows the
history behind these two gentlemen and
the history the and the Very uh fraught
history that the U.S and the Saudis have
the past five or so years the whole
world knows this and the fact that Mr
Modi was able to get these two guys
together and have them shake hands
that's uh you know this is highly
symbolic and it's important
it tells us that India is able to get
things done and and have India is able
to make people resolve differences and
Patch differences up and come together
despite differences
so this this kind of tells you that
India's stature in India's importance in
the world is genuinely Rising
I mean if if it was not Mr Modi if it
was somebody else from some other
country I don't think that person would
have been able to get these two guys
together
uh especially considering the treatment
that Mr Muhammad bin Salman was given in
previous G20 Summits very poor treatment
very very
cold treatment by the same countries
that are now well
quite warm towards it so yeah I think I
think it's great I think it's great
uh
what else do we have
the new trade route from India to Europe
shows new alignment where Israel is
working with two strong Arab Nations so
turkey China and Pakistan's response
would be what what should be we be ready
for
in Pakistan look birds of a feather
flock together turkey and Pakistan have
a lot in common the Turks overall they
don't like the pakistanis they don't
like Indians as well okay
and that's that's a from that comes from
a racist perspective racist perspective
but but keeping them aside uh
so like I mentioned like I said some
time ago the India Middle East uh Europe
trade Corridor is a direct challenge to
China's built enrolled initiative it's a
direct direct
competitor it's something that aims to
replace that
and with this new trade out trade regard
opening up it's gonna be
an incentive for Many Nations
to choose India's credit card or rather
than China's Trader
and Pakistan has been part of the Bri
Pakistani you've had the China Pakistan
economic Corridor I'm sure you're all
aware of that the cpec which is well
which is dead
what's happening there the Chinese
invested like I don't know how many
billion dollars there what happened
show me a single project that come to
fruition
so that's dead so what can the Chinese
and the pakistanis and the Turks do well
Pakistan nobody wants to be wants to
have their hands
nobody wants to be involved in Pakistan
I think even Mr Xi Jinping and his
minions minions no
that Pakistan is a temporary Nation look
I once again I'm not being flippant I'm
not making fun of Pakistan I I know the
people in Pakistan who are our blood
relatives from from India's perspective
they are facing terrible times but
listen
what can I say the pakistanis have been
bleeding India for the past 70 years so
please don't expect me to care too much
and to feel very sorry really sorry I I
really feel bad for the people of
Pakistan that well that's how it's good
that's just the way history works the
cycles of history work like that
National borders change artificial
Nations disintegrate Pakistan is an
artificial nation and Pakistan is a
temporary Nation I wonder how long it
will last
maybe three years maybe five maybe one
year who knows
um it seems that like certain parts of
Pakistani territory are already no
longer gone by the by the Army right
so um I don't think Pakistan is a nation
of much consequence today
Pakistan what can Pakistan respond I
mean in what way can Pakistan respond to
India Pakistan is is no longer in the
same league I mean it's not even one
tenth of the league of India anymore you
know that's how far India has has
progressed in the past nine ten years
so in the past the Americans would
insist on hyphenating India and Pakistan
India Pakistan India Pakistan India
Pakistan well today the entire
hyphenation has changed China nobody
talks about Pakistan anymore for good
reason India is no longer in the same
league as Pakistan India is Way Way Gone
way ahead of that so who cares what
Pakistan's responses is going to be a
nation that's hardly standing on one
foot how can a response respond what can
turkey do turkey doesn't have the funds
to create uh a parallel infrastructure
any any infrastructure any trade
Corridor that can compete with something
that India and the Europeans can come up
with and please remember the way that
Turks don't like India and Pakistan or
India let's say India I think Europeans
don't like turkey either by the way
the Europeans aren't fond of turk turkey
remember that so my dear Turkish friends
may be watching this and Allah saying
that we hate India
or we hate Indians
for for the for the racist reasons that
that many of them give well the
Europeans see you the same way I'm
really sorry to say that
okay
so uh turkey doesn't have the fun sort
of very with all to come up with
something that can challenge or compete
with the India the the forthcoming India
middle east Europe trade Corridor China
has the funds but nobody wants to deal
with China
Italy has pulled out of the Bri other
nations will also put out of the Bri the
Bri is I nearly half dead
what's happening what new infrastructure
has been built and where is it being
built nowhere
okay so these are all kinds of
propaganda on social media there are
lots of propagandists
um China and Russia have some sort of a
modus they are working together to some
extent but the Russians obviously with
good reason don't trust China so I don't
think China see if you if you are a
bullying
if you're a bully and if you are very
poorly behaved nobody will work with you
no matter how rich you are that that
applies to Nations that applies to
individuals as well you know you got to
have some manners you're gonna have some
respect for others
and that only that can only happen if it
if it is genuinely something that you
are
so China is by at least the Chinese
Communist Party Chinese people are nice
I I think most Chinese people are really
nice people
and we've had 2 000 years of good
relations with China it's only after the
goddamn Communist Party Chinese
Communist Party invaded an annexed Tibet
with Mr nehru's approval the great
magnificent Mr nehru that's where things
went wrong between India and China it's
a Chinese aggression that caused all the
friction
so the Chinese Communist Party the
Chinese Communist Party sees itself as
some kind of new Imperial Dynasty and
they seek to rule the world and they're
very transparent about it they're very
crass very transparent very pushy very
they're real bullies and nobody likes
that
so even though China right now has the
money I don't think they're going to be
able to get a lot of Nations on board so
if Nations like India and the uh the uh
UAE Saudi Arabia and the European
nations and the US come together and
offer a really good alternative to
China's Bri I think lots of Nations will
jump at it and I think that's the
beginning that's what we are saying we
are seeing the beginning of that so I
don't think there's going to be any real
response worth noting that's gonna come
from turkey and Pakistan then China may
try something and they may you know
issue some are strong statements who
cares
keep talking
words it's all talk
okay
Krishna Agarwal says what are your views
on XI jinping's absence in the G20
and his health problem thing I don't
know what his health problems he's had a
history of health problems or alleged
health problems when he became the
Chinese Premier or the Chinese Supreme
Darth Vader
which year was it 2012. I think he went
on a few months of vacation before he
even assumed the the leadership of China
to deal with some health issue so I
don't know what that is he he
seems to have an apparent history of
certain health problems but there's no
transparency transparency on that I
don't think he has chosen to skip the
summit for any health issue I think it's
a defensive move
I think he also knows that nobody at the
G20 high table really likes him
he also knows that he has this major
issue major problem that he has created
with India huge friction all because of
Chinese aggression the deaths that
happened in galwan on both sides were
because of Chinese aggression Chinese
are solely responsible for that
and
all the Border disputes there with
various stations including Russia who's
created those issues the Chinese have
created that and they have this terribly
uh this increasingly tense relationship
with the US
the U.S
essentially imposed various kinds of
sanctions from the Chinese when it comes
to semiconductors and so on and so forth
so there's this very tense relationship
with the US it's not a good relationship
it's it's a
it's a rough relationship
uh and if in Nations like like like like
uh France and Germany in Italy they're
gonna be on the U.S side
right
um so essentially there is no warmth for
Mr Xi Jinping at the G20 high table Mr
Putin is absent and Mr Putin also
doesn't trust me and Mr Modi and Mr Xi
Jinping don't have a good relationship
entirely because of the actions of Mr
xinping
uh Mr Modi and she met briefly very
briefly in Bali in last year's T20
Summit they also met very briefly in
South Africa
during the recent brick Summit but
that's about it very brief interactions
and not very friendly interactions for
good reason so Xi Jinping
one of the reasons he did not come is
because he expected and rightfully so a
cold not very uh warm welcome in New
Delhi not only from his host Mr nirendra
Modi but also from the other world
leaders nobody would have any warmth for
him
so they would not ignore him the way
they once ignored Muhammad bin Salman
but there there won't be any special
warm welcome for him
the other reason
is that the Chinese are kind of jealous
of the way the Indians have conducted
the G20 presidency India has taken it to
a whole different level
more than 60 cities more than 130 events
across the length and the breadth of the
country including in in jamun Kashmir
including in arunachal Pradesh
and India has shown off its incredibly
vibrant diverse culture of the
incredible energy of its youth it's it's
increasingly uh sophisticated and
Powerful technological capabilities
infrastructure so much
India has done what nobody else has done
with this one year's presidency this one
year term of the G20 presidency and
at the end
um it was going to be a successful
Summit even if all the leaders did not
agree upon a joint declaration well now
we we even have that so it's the icing
on the cake so the Chinese are kind of
jealous not kind of but actually jealous
of what India has achieved during this
one year India took initiated that
nobody else took and India has been
positioning itself as the leader of the
global South India has ensured
single-handedly that the African Union
is not now part of the G20 the g21 the
Chinese have never pushed for that so
because India did such a good job the
Chinese are jealous and maybe Mr Sheila
being thought that if he doesn't come
he's going to take some Sheen away from
the G20 Summit well haha
a very Petty cynical move
a very negative and defensive move but
it's come to nothing it's come to
nothing
and what it the message it has sent the
world
is that China is not a serious and
responsible Nation
the G20 is about solving problems
it's about it's about taking the world
forward
in in us right in the good direction
it's about dealing with big issues like
climate with the energy crisis with uh
Fuel and fertilizers and stuff like that
then China doesn't want to be part of
that that's the message it it gives to
the world China wants to be part of the
brics
where it's the biggest thing around
it doesn't want to be part of the G20 it
doesn't want to participate
is number two
so it sends a very uh negative message
to the world about China that China is
not a responsible power and China is not
serious about any responsibilities that
it claims to have taken on
so overall it's a very negative move
it's a very cynical move it's a
defensive move it's a petty jealous move
they even they even objected to the term
I mean how much more Petty can you get
so I think you know Mr Xi Jinping has
done the world favor by not coming
who wants is his presence over here
who wants a shadow in New Delhi it's a
good thing he did the world and India a
favor by not turning up his number two
was mostly invisible it's the king Q Ing
and the summit went off really well
it would have been
a kind of a burden to have him over here
so Mr Xi Jinping thank you very much for
not coming I don't think you have any
health issue you were just Petty and
jealous and even by not turning up you
ended up failing because the summit went
off really well the most successful G20
Summit in history
there you go
okay
LOL what else
all vegetarian food very nice food all
vegetarian okay
what else
okay we already
dealt with Africa
okay
uh is there anything was anything
mentioned about Niger in the meeting
while none of I mean I I saw all the
official live telecasts the broadcasts
uh and there was no mention of media or
anything Nisha is is not the G20
grouping of Nations is not a
geopolitical computations the what's on
the agenda is trade and and development
and the economy and certain other issues
geopolitics is off the table what's
happening is in media is a geopolitical
issue it's about the people of Nigeria
and and the co-leaders who have popular
support it's about them rising up
against European or more specifically
French neocolonialism
that's what this coup is about
and there's no point discussing that in
this meeting it's it's the meeting is
not for that purpose it's not a it
doesn't have any kind of geopolitical
agenda so there was no mention as far as
I know or Niger in the meeting
Bobby says don't you think you should
have both names one to address yourself
internally and own him and the other one
in exonim which is how others address
you Bharat versus India look I am
perfectly well happy with with the
country having two names two official
names India and Bharat so whoever within
the country wants to refer to Nation as
Bharat shall do that and the rest of the
world can do what they're more
comfortable with and more accustomed to
which is calling
the country India now other nations have
also recently there are certain other
nations that have recently renamed
themselves for example turkey has called
has renamed itself or rebranded itself
as turkey a
turkey a uh there is a Czech Republic
which is now check here
uh what else do we have yeah two I can
think of it which became is no no no no
no no Swaziland which became and so on
so some Nations have done that and well
how many people call turkey turkey a
today
and how many people call the Czech
Republic
so
all right it doesn't matter I don't care
what what others want to call us I don't
really care let them say whatever they
want to do
um
so I think it's not a bad idea to have
two names and so I agree with Bobby here
let's have two names Bharat and India uh
this certain amount of brand value also
attached to the term India I mean are
you gonna call the Indian Ocean the
bharatiya ocean now uh I don't I mean
I'm nothing against that I mean I called
the South China Sea the champasi right
but that's the process that will take
time brands do change over time
for example Twitter is now X it's it's
people still call it Twitter but in a
couple of years they're gonna call it X
I'm sure so these things happen
so I think it's it's a it should be a
more natural organic process in which
people see I mean there are cities like
Mumbai
that Mumbai used to be called Bombay
some people still say Bombay but most
people now say Mumbai Chennai used to be
Madras some I'm not sure if people still
say Madras everyone says as far as I
know so in some cases it takes longer in
some places in some cases it's it's
faster I think overall let the two
official names then you can have a slow
gradual organic
in the natural transition to the actual
civilization name which can take maybe
20 years maybe 50 years maybe 100 days I
don't care
so right now I think it makes sense to
have two official names but yeah I'll be
very happy if more people call the
nation Bharat
right what other questions do we have
why can't do India do salaam is slicing
with Pakistan
you can slice salami which is a certain
consistency but you can't slice
cookies
you know cookies crumble you try to try
to slice it then it crumbles
so Pakistan is kind of in in that sort
of situation right now you've got to
slice it slice it it's gonna crumble I
think Pakistan sadly is for them is just
a matter of time it's gonna crumble
so uh yeah let it happen on its own why
why do salaam is slicing or anything
um
okay what else
okay says what's the global biofuel
Alliance that's been launched recently
many are betting on biofuel there are
companies working on producing biofuel
unique Marine using Marine algae and
seaweeds in Bharat as well So This
Global biofuel Alliance that was
launched recently today I'm not sure
very recently by Prime Minister Modi is
a new initiative that uh
that caused a bond
Nations
to use a 20 ethanol blending in in
petrol gasoline the U.S the Americans
called it gasoline we call it Patrol
so right now I think India Blends about
10 ethanol what is ethanol ethanol is
ethyl alcohol
what's the chemical formula it's kind of
Rusty I was good at organic chemistry
but what is it
okay it's ethanol it's it's green
alcohol it is a synthetic chemical which
is also something that occurs naturally
through fermentation it's a recreational
drug it's part of every single
thing that people drink you know beer
rum whiskey whatever that's what it is
now if you take pure alcohol and you mix
it with the petrol it works very well
and so
um India like I said uses 10 percent
blending so 90 petrol and 10 ethanol I
think there are several European nations
that also do this 90 petrol 10 ethanol
and that kind of reduces the amount of
carbon emissions that are emitted uh the
amount of carbon monoxide that's given
off by the burning of the of this Fuel
and also the amount of hydrocarbons that
are emitted as as the as part of the
exhaust of the vehicles now if you
increase that blending to 20
the carbon monoxide emissions and the
hydrocarbon emissions
are reduced even further
so the global biofuel Alliance is about
urging Nations to adopt a 20 blending
standard
so that's India's initiative just like
the global solar Alliance and I think
India is going to take uh steps to
ensure that it starts blending uh
ethanol up to 20 so ethanol is produced
by uh fermenting uh sugarcane
and sugar and molasses and other
agricultural based products it can also
be made by by fermenting um
spoiled grains like wheat and rice and
whatnot if your grain gets boiled you
can take it and ferment it and produce
ethanol out of it and like some of us
are saying you can even do that using
Marine algae and seaweeds I'm sure there
are processes for doing that as well so
so that's what this Global biofuel
Alliance is it's about
um
it's about blending ethanol to 20 in in
petrol and as a consequence uh
you know having less emissions less
carbon emissions and reducing the burden
on the planet that's what it's about
and it's an Indian initiative
yeah
Sagar on which map if you have a map
printed in Hindi it may be called
hinmasagar but globally in maps of the
world whenever you have non-indian
languages it's called the Indian Ocean
so yeah we have lots of names we can
also call it bharatiya samudra or
whatever
Okay so that's all right but even the
word hind is an exoner it comes from the
word
the name of a great river which still
exists and the portions of our ancient
cousins could not pronounce sir they had
lost the ability to pronounce sir so
they replaced that with her and that's
how became Hindu and which gave rise to
the name Hind and so on so even the word
hind is in EXO name
all right let's understand that so the
correct word is Bharat but it will take
some time for that to be adopted
all right what else do we have
[Music]
um
sabana says should China be kicked out
from the G20 I don't think that will
happen China is way too powerful way too
important to be ignored to that extent
uh when it comes to Russia Russia is I
think the ninth or the 10th largest
economy in the world so you can kind of
do that and obviously there are other
issues with Russia as well so I don't
think that China will be kicked out from
the G20 I don't think there's any move
to to do that I don't think there are
any calls to do that
um
and I don't think it's necessary or even
desirable to kick China or from T20 what
do you achieved by doing that what do
you achieve I mean is there any tangible
beneficial outcome for anybody by
kicking off China they will still do
what they're doing
it's just being like spiteful and Petty
but it achieves nothing you know that's
the thing ah yeah so so that's something
right so I don't think that's gonna
happen or even if it's really desirable
uh so hansraj says it's c2h5oh
ch4oh is methyl alcohol and c2h5oh is
ethyl alcohol yeah good thank you I I
hope you're right I think it sounds
about right it's been a long time since
I looked into organic chemistry but yeah
I think you're right about this
so so thank you sir thank you
okay
Samana Satish I I'm sorry if I've
mispronounced your name uh are there
discussions about electric electric
vehicles I heard that India wants to
reach its use of ev's Target by 2032.
um what Target does India have 30 EVS 10
percent EVS I'm not sure what it is
um so I am not aware of any discussions
about electric vehicles in in this uh in
today's
sessions of the G20 Summit
um so I don't think they were discussed
I will have to look at look at the Joint
declaration to see if there is a
dimension of electric vehicles but uh I
don't remember
sharing about that today
uh so yeah as far as I know there wasn't
this wasn't discussed but uh I'll double
check
declaration to make sure that it wasn't
there so let's see
um yeah India India is taking lead when
it comes to uh green technologies
renewable technology renewable energy
uh and yes I think India's India is
targeting 10 or 30 electric vehicle
penetration by Twenty by Twenty Thirty
twenty thirty dollars of thereabouts
um so yeah I think India is taking the
lead in these things and it's a it's a
very good initiative it shows that India
is very is way more responsible than
China is for example you know yeah
okay
okay what else
can the G20 give India any economic
growth opportunity that's what random
asks
so we just discussed I I cracked out the
map didn't we didn't I so we discussed
the uh India middle east Europe trade
Corridor which is going to involve real
links and shipping links as well it's
gonna have a an electrical uh connection
electrical power cable is going to have
a hydrogen pipeline it's going to have a
high speed data cable that's going to
open up lots of kind of growth
opportunities trade opportunities so the
G20 is all about trade and the economy
it's about Nations coming together
talking about trade and economy and
furthering their interests in in a
variety of mutually beneficial ways so
it's all about economic growth
opportunities that's the entire that's
the whole point of the G20 the G20 is
not about geomolytics it's about
economics it's about trade it's about
Finance that's what it's about so yes of
course it will it's this thing that I
just mentioned the uh India
middle east Europe
Corridor the trade Corridor the trade
thing that itself is gonna open up lots
of economic growth opportunities so yes
the answer is yes
okay
not sure why India's Indians are getting
excited so excited about Vivek ramaswamy
running for U.S elections take a look at
any benefit for India so look
any
U.S citizen of whatever origin is going
to prioritize their natural interest or
everything else that has to be
understood Indians I'm you know talk
today Dr Subhash kak put out a tweet
that Indians are very emotional people
it's something I have personally said
many times on on this channel Indians
are a very emotional people everything
is about emotions
and Indians many Indians don't think
rationally
he's our guy the skin color is similar
to mine yeah good what
what tangible
you have what's your name
Google you have such an Adela the boss
of Microsoft I mean what benefit have
they given to India do you see Google
Maps and you see the the boundaries that
are recently represented and you see if
you if you click on with that
let's do it let's demonstrate okay let's
let's hide the point it's going to waste
unnecessary time the point is these
people are U.S citizens and they're
gonna prioritize the well-being and
Welfare and the interests of the US this
is what's something that every Indian
has to understand Indians get so excited
and so emotional about things
so easily so you know what it's nice to
have Vivek ramas for me it's going to
bring more visibility to Indians to to
Indian Americans and to India overall
but it's not going to benefit India okay
he's going to prioritize his nationality
just look at his look at his statements
look at everything they're saying look
at his foreign policy that he's putting
out it's all about the U.S
and I would not compare Rama Swami with
Mark is more of an appointee than an
elective
um and once again what's the benefit for
India so yes I agree with SRI Kumar he's
a very valid point
um
Spartan bhagava says did Putin ever want
Russia to join nato in the past uh when
Putin was a newly minted fresh fresh
President of Russia he actually wanted
Russia to join Ukraine well today he has
learned a lot of lessons and he's no
longer that the naive so yes he did want
to join NATO and the NATO all the
Americans just laughed it off laughed at
him who the who the hell do you think
you are joining NATO that sort of thing
so yes once he was naive he was a more
idealistic perhaps
and uh yeah so he learned his lesson he
didn't want to join he did want Russia
to join NATO well that's never going to
happen
okay
British says could the state of Texas
gain independence
ah well you never know there's been
a sporadic Texas Independence Movement
the Lone Star State
uh someday it may happen because well
you see the US is occupied territory
the U.S is is a nation that's created as
a result of secular colonialism and the
ones who wanted Texas to succeed were
themselves uh settlers but yeah
so in the immediate field in the future
in the near future I don't see any such
thing happening but at the distant
future it may happen
um
and India soon become a permanent member
of the unfc soon no I don't think so by
2030 maybe who knows
but there is a huge amount of resistance
right now from essentially from the
Chinese
uh
they don't want India to have the same
status at the same Powers as then
in the United Nations security Council
even the other nations are very
reluctant to see this happen
I mean the U.N security Council the the
composition of the U.N security Council
is is something that was decided in 1945
roughly in 1945 the victors of the
second world war were given those
Privileges and that's a time that's like
almost essentially ago now and we're
still living by that it's like the
Indian constitution which was drafted by
who knows
what people and who knows when
you know things need to change
so uh I don't think it will happen soon
but eventually no one can stop India
we're gonna be there we're going to be
everywhere
we kind of already are everywhere aren't
we when you go to Niagara Falls
you'll feel like Niagara Falls is in
India and some foreigners are there just
to see it but most of us are Indians
around here so we are anyway everywhere
but we can assume matter a lot more
okay let's take a few more questions
a few more questions
um
okay what is this are there any
expectations on Space technology collabs
from tomorrow's session I'm not sure if
space is going to be on the table or on
the agenda
uh when it comes to space technology
collaborations ISRO does collaborate
with various space agencies uh the the
current chandrayaan three Mission the
the Lander I believe it it has an
instrument a retro reflector that's been
um given to them by by NASA it's a
passive instrument it's something you
bounce laser beams off of to measure the
precise distance between Earth the Earth
and the moon so there's some
collaboration with NASA uh India has in
the past Israel has in the past
collaborated with uh roskos Moss the
Russian the Russian space agency not a
very fruitful collaboration but and
there's some collaboration with Japan as
well so I think we'll do that but I
don't think it's something that's going
to be on the G20 Edge and of course I
could be wrong and something would
happen tomorrow and if it does I will
report about it I'll talk about it but
as far as I know I don't think it's on
the agenda but I'll see you tomorrow
right
says how do you look at the U.S as a
military power house compared to Russia
and China
um when it comes to Russia and the U.S
Russia has a larger nuclear Arsenal so
Russia is is frightfully dangerous and
frightfully scary from that perspective
from the size of the nuclear Arsenal uh
when it comes to Conventional Weapons
nobody can beat the US and the U.S has
the ability to intervene militarily
anywhere in the world at 30 to 60
minutes notice no other country comes
even close to that so you can't even
compare Russia and China with the US
when it comes to that ability
so I am very clear about this there's
only one superpower in the world which
is the us we no longer live in a
multi-polar in a unipolar world like we
were living in between 1991 and
2016-2017 we are now entering an era of
multipolarity but there's still only one
superpower it's the US uh Russia is not
a superpower but Russia is a major
nuclear power the Chinese are more of an
economic Powerhouse not quite in
military
they do they do have a powerful military
but they still can't even take Taiwan
you know the U.S has more powerful
across the Taiwan Strait right in
China's back door backyard that's how
powerful the US is so you can't really
compare China with the US yeah
foreign
some questions are being repeated which
is okay some people may have joined late
so in that case that in Marine blind
once this is done
uh what else do we have
what do you choose Bharat or India
I choose look
I think uh from a non-emotional from a
practical perspective I I would say we
should keep both
but from a deep emotional
civilizational cultural perspective it
obviously has to be part of
but
um
I think we need to be practical I think
we should keep both for now for now I
think it may be a little too early to
complete give up the term India I think
right now we should keep both
but eventually in the long run we showed
a reward to
the official name of Bharat
okay
is finally more towards the West
look India Bharat is the only nation
that is has except relations with both
Russia and the West
and Bharat will do
whatever is in its interests in its best
interests
now take this very simple scenario we
have this large neighbor
an aggressive imperialistic expansionist
neighbor China
now let's say China and India go to war
which should be started by China India
is not going to start any War the
Chinese will if they do
in case there's a war in case the
Chinese start a war with India
who is likely to help India materially
not verbally we don't care about words
materially is it is Russia in a position
to help India versus China if a war
happens the Russians will stay neutral
they'll stay out of it they are not
strong enough to intervene
the Americans with certainly
be more likely to intervene and help
India materially in a variety of ways
likely not guaranteed they'll be likely
to do it but I'm like you can't
guarantee that either but the likelihood
is way higher the U.S compared to Russia
so it makes sense to have good relations
with the West because there is a
convergence of interests
so yeah if you if you look at it from
that perspective it may look like
India's leaning more towards the West
will India will do whatever is in its
best interests if the West is giving
India what it needs from the perspective
of Technology from the perspective of
trade the perspective of diplomatic
support geopolitical support why should
we not lean a little bit more in that
side what is Russia offering to us
of course we are not cutting off our
ties with Russia we still have good
relations with the Russians Mr Modi and
Mr Putin still have a excellent
relationship
so India Russia relations aren't
deteriorating there's no deterioration
but India's Outreach with the West is
kind of stronger these days well why not
so it just makes sense from the logic of
strategy from a geopolitical perspective
um okay
it's okay
uh
Heyman says why are you still there what
time is it in India it's 10 30 in the
Night 10 30 in the PM it's kind of late
to be here isn't it I should be back at
the hotel
um I just thought I'd do this it's been
such a long time since I did a live
stream and just give you guys video guys
and girls and others
a look at how things are over here I
just thought I'd do it and they have
provided extremely good internet over
here the wired internet the Lan cable
extremely fast like like almost a GP one
gbps nearly you know so I thought let's
take advantage of that and do a good
live stream and reconnect it's been a
while something like that so uh I agree
it's it's very late I should get back to
the hotel uh Delhi is kind of under
lockdown right now uh it's it's hard to
get a taxi I'm sure they will offer me a
shuttle bus but I'm not sure it'll take
me to the hotel
it will take me somewhere else when I
don't want to be somewhere else so I
love to get myself a taxi so I think
I'll take a few more questions and then
wrap this up but yeah so yes I shouldn't
be here
too longer this place
this International media center
is going to be open all night
so if I choose to I can stay here all
night till tomorrow morning also
obviously they're not very good for my
health you don't need a few hours of
sleep so I think I'll
choose
caution or Valor and I will go back to
the hotel soon and sleep uh before I do
that let me take maybe to three more
questions
um
uh
says
what's the future of the Arctic as I
spelled who will control this valuable
region well if you look at the map where
is the map here's the map we've got to
see the map for this
what is the map
here's the map
so if you take a look at the Arctic
region not the Antarctic you will see
that Russia
is it has a huge presence there
use that Canada and U.S Enterprise there
the Russians sold Alaska to the
Americans so the Americans have a
presence there and I once uh had a
question from somebody from these uh
from
from diabetes I think the little one
which is in the Arctic region anyway
that's a completely
it's a complete digression so Russia has
a huge presence there the American
server presence the Canadian server
presence the Danes of Denmark have a
presence Norway has a presence and so
does Finland
so these nations have a presence there
now if you look at these nations there's
only two real big Powers there the
Americans and the Russians
so and and the Chinese are also
interested in the Arctic region
uh
and with Russia's consent they may also
you know establish some kind of presence
there especially if it helps Russia uh
monetarily Financial economically
geopolitically so I think as the ice
melts the Americans and the Russians who
have the major stake in the Arctic
region the Chinese may buy their way
into it so that's how it is uh I don't
think India has any major plans right
now for that but we'll see we'll see so
mainly the U.S and Russia Russia
okay
okay what else
uh
Bobby says well if China China
is a so-called near Arctic so is India
well if China is India yeah it makes
sense for this thing but you've got to
build the
deep the economic heft and you've got to
build a few ice breakers because it's
it's still going to be ice Bound in the
winters you know
um I'm okay
what else do we have
um
oh yeah nobody mentioned
Justin Bieber
how is the studio meltdown coming
um I did see him somewhere
in the mix but I don't think he has much
of a presence today
um so yeah I don't know where the
Meltdown is coming but I did see his
face briefly who met him it was I think
it was Minister who I met recently who
went to receive uh
Justin Trudeau at the airport but I
don't think he's been really very active
or very very very uh visible this time
uh all this mlbb thank you sir
appreciate it
um
what have you been dreaming lately on
the Arctic I think I think India should
be making a presence in Antarctica
you're closer than just about anyone
even though it's halfway around the
world you know Argentina and Chile have
a
have a very uh
significant proximity to Antarctica so
does Australia as well as New Zealand
um and even the French have certain
islands in the region close to
Antarctica
so yeah it's it's another interesting
mix that we have when it comes to
Antarctica but for India it's a straight
line it's great straight road to
Antarctica you just if you are let's say
you are in standing on the beaches of
saurashtra
did you just take a ship and go straight
South in Norwegian doctor nothing's
gonna come in the way
so I think India should dream bigger
we need to dream bigger in many fields
in many domains and they should think
about the Arctic and they should think
of the Antarctic India should think
about Landing two or three Indians on
the Moon by 2035 on chandrayaan 10. we
will need to dream big and I hope we are
doing that
okay let me take one more question
health is great thank you so much
um
looking to get into a relationship with
women
who who should please be in charge of
the relationship and wouldn't be okay my
future wife what's the job same as me ah
listen it depends on each person every
every case is unique
I I I don't know I am a geopolitical
analyst I am not really a somebody who
is qualified to advise about
relationships I mean maybe I am but uh
that's something I don't do I don't
think
it should work out for you you know the
right person
and
then it depends on what works for both
of you
I guess that's it
uh there are no hard and fast rules each
case is unique each individual you know
people come to me I mean in the airports
and all you know young kids
they come and ask me what should I do uh
I'm I'm in engineering my dad wants to
wants me to go abroad but I want to join
the IAS what should I do I tell them I
don't know personally so I don't know
each person is unique you should
maximize your potential you should do
something that maximizes your potential
and uh you know
if you really want to serve the nation
First Serve Yourself first be something
somebody of consequence and then then
you can serve the nature so you know
that's the thing you can't give hard and
fast advice which is like one size fits
all each person is unique so Giuseppe I
don't know personally so I can't tell
you you know what will work for you but
uh
yeah so each case is unique and overall
I I don't see anything wrong with it
with your partner your your wife working
but yeah it's up to you and her I guess
okay let's take one more questions
um
more questions
one more question one more question
[Music]
uh what should I pick okay let's just
take this one all those mlbb says do do
you think more people need to be
educated in the fact that Moguls were
difficult
I think it should be taught in textbooks
you look at the the 1757 of whichever
year it was map of India colored map of
India you'll see there are no mughals
anywhere
in the 18th century and it is the
British who defeated the marathas of the
mughals so there are lots of
well-educated people who come and claim
that the British saved India from the
mughals those people are absolute I
don't know what what term to use I I can
think of a few terms but I will not
utter those words here
the language of Mordor
so you know that's the problem with lots
of Indians they think they they know
everything
and the unfortunately seemed to be not
fair of basic historical facts so yes I
agree that everybody in India is
educating about the fact that the
mughals were destroyed they were
defeated
who wiped them out almost entirely
was reduced to being the mayor of not
just Delhi not only not even Delhi only
of the Red Fort that's it
so yeah uh people do need to be educated
about them uh right I think with that
I'm gonna wrap up this session it's not
quite a tour session but it's already
over 90 minutes so a decent uh
respectable length so
um so thank you everybody for attending
this I really appreciate it and it's
glad to do this it's really nice to do
this again and I'm gonna revert back to
doing this more often the Oscar widget
show so thank you everyone for attending
for watching for all your questions
apologies to those of you those
questions I could not take which is most
of you unfortunately but anyway thank
you so much and uh I will see you
hopefully very soon in the next
ask Abhijit episode until then take care
and keep praising keep raising your
standards bye